It's a little lame good morning everybody.
That's a lot better...build conference gone so far
awesome isn't that what is the best session...seen all day.
I want to welcome you all to build welcome you all to an exciting new
...development I want to welcome the online viewers that are watching this live-in those that are going to watch this
...recorded version of this that's why we had such...
Orchestrated start to the session here.
...talk about is adders next generation compute platform got a bunch of announcements to make
in the session and a bunch of really cool demos to show you in the session as well.
This is the weather obstruction the session the kind of take you from the very top-level because we
can't talk about compute without talking about adders overall application model which we call the as
resource manager all talk about that for those of you that might
not be familiar with it...something that is already jade but what I'll do it from there is
take you into some of the new api that are plugged into
as a resource manager that we're announcing today and those are around virtual machines
storage and networking resources completely changing the way that you interact with
these types of resources in...
And, then I'll talk about service fabric which we announced we pre announced last week...
the blog post what you're going to get here is an sdk to play with service fabric for those you
didn't see the blog maybe don't know what service fabric is I'm going to give me give you
a pretty detailed overview of service fabric which are really excited about which is
a micros service-based orchestration platform let's go and get started talk about as
...manager just out of curiosity how many people have used as
your resource manager so just a few of you those of you
...been using...for sometime a problem using cloud services and the existing portal
will resource manager is a different way of looking at
...applications
let-me set some context here because if you take a look at the original cloud service application model,
you know, that was just focused on compute and network and it left a lot of the glue
of connecting other types of...services including even just storage to those
gm's that you're putting in their cloud services up to you if you
...website you deployed a website and then you deployed a database and
it was up to you to glue those together with as a resource manager
we define this concept of resource grouping where you can group collections
...resources together that make-up the whole application or part of a larger application.
Each resource instance that you put into a research group is a of a resource type and
I've already
mentioned some of the resource types like virtual machines like databases like storage accounts.
And, those resource types are defined by what we call research providers the as a resource managers
completely extensible so it comes with a number of built-in resource providers that provide that
define their own resource types but when we want to add a new research provider to the as
your platform ourselves there's no need to go change as a resource manager other than
register the resource provider in the types that it's going to support where.
We've already on boarded some third-party research providers as well
and you'll cs light up the on boarding process so that others more and more
you can onboard your own resource providers into this model now one of the concepts here
that we're sticking to is that resource groups art
concepts deeply baked in the platform there's no such thing as a resource now
...asher that is not part of a resource group so when you...just create a...account
if that's the only thing you're interested in you're still putting in a container which is a resource group.
What you get by putting these things in these containers is that you get lifecycle management
of the whole collection of resources that make-up this logical entity that you're interested in grouping
together so you get the ability to deploy them all together and I'll show you how we support
declared of deployment of resource groups you get
to update them together so if you got updates that span a bunch of these
resource instances those updates can be done through single api is into as
a resource manager you-can delete the whole research group together so this is a way for you to say I'm
done with all these this application of this part of this application
...delete it all of the constituent resources
get deleted automatically and then you can create the status of the resource group the aggregated status research group
and you can drill into the resource group and query their status as well?
This groupings useful...other places to,
for example, you're going to cs add more and more capabilities around putting
...meter ing and quotas on resource groups you can say that this resource group can only
create and number of...and no more...create x amount of storage
in storage accounts and no more you'll be able to set billing limits on resource
groups you'll be able to also and this is already there take a look at your
resource group status from this collection perspective from the portals.
To the command lines interfaces to adder to the rest api
...as well as powerful and then it's also
scope for our back so this is the way we're introducing our back into the control plains of
address through as a research groups and as a resource manager we can define our back rules that are
scoped to a resource group or to resources or even some resources in a resource group so you
could say that only the owners of the resource group can have
...access to the...m in the resource group, for example.
And, then something that you can cs coming is identity's going to be built into resource groups
to so resource groups will have their own identity provision
and abstracted directory and using this identity all of the resources in that
resource group will have the ability to talk to each other without you having to provide credentials
...or certificates for them to have some identity to talk to outside services they
will appear as first-class principles measure active directory this will allow them to talk to
each other these resources inside the research group as well as
to outside resources that are able to speak...off protocol to interact with these.
And, one of the questions that I often get when I talk about research group says I've got some resources
...I put them in a research group versus put them in separate resource groups an answer that question is
actually fairly simple and straightforward do they have common lifecycle
and management operations that you want to perform on them if, for example,
you've got a marketing database and you've got to front-ends to that maybe
one is an internal front-end that's going and putting data in the marketing database and the other
one is customer-facing application that's also making use of that data and marketing database
well those are three different resources that likely have different life cycles and
...want to put those each in the separate resource groups
...front-ends though might have their own middle tears that are part of them that are part of that
...that front-end so...to put those inside the same resource group.
The resource group manager services so resource group manager there's a front-end to
adders called research group manager and it provides a bunch of services
that all of the resources there part of this model get for free, for example, centralize auditing of
operations because it is the control plane badger you get basically a
...log of all the control...operations and I've got a screenshot
...from the...portal showing you that you get tagging...resources
sell this is useful if you want to be able to tag resources
...perform queries like which resources are tagged marketing department because
knows resources are related whatever the marketing departments doing and you can
buy tagging resources do those kinds of queries this tagging will also be integrated
in the billing systems so that you can go and say how much did the marketing department cost me last month and
by evaluating those tags and looking at the bills for...resources over the last month you'll see
a summary of how much that cost you and then finally like I mentioned it's a consistent place for
our back with the...member built-in roles and research providers can define are only
rules and get that for themselves for their own resource types all
implementing a consistent way through this control...
One of the most exciting parts about resource...for me is the fact that it's got template
...deployments so you can interact with resource manager using rest api
and perform imperative operations the build-up a resource group so, for example, you can say go creative
...and creative storage account both in the same resource group but
were moved into a world where imperative creation
of resources of applications is something that is
...reproduce double and fragile so we've gone to at least within manager a
more declarative approach to defining what applications look like and what
...approach comes the template describes exactly what you want
the application to look like in this case a resource group so, for example,
I want...website with the database and I want to database connection string to go into
a input parameter on that website instead of me having to do something out
of banned by putting this in a template I can describe those
relationships and give it to add resource manager I can parameterized the template so
that I can deploy into multiple places and get the same experience everywhere I go
just by supplying different parameters depending on environment so I can deployed into a test environment
which test parameters I can deploy to production environment with
production and parameters I might want a single instance version of
my application in...production I want to be multi and since for scale
out for availability and I can do that just by changing parameters but the template
itself describing the structure of the application is unchanged and I can check...source control?
The way that...template execution works as a resource manager takes a look
and this is another advantage of having something that's...rather than imperative is that the as
a resource manager can examine the relationship between the resources that are in
the template and find the fastest path forward
to get that operations executed so, for example,
I've got an app service plan which is what I deploy web apps and logic apps
onto I might...website on to it I put
auto scaling on top of that after that completes there's some dependencies that...some resources the
head dependencies on that website coming up like app insights on alert rule on the
website cpu usage and maybe a
...microsoft deploy packages depending on the website coming up before that those can activate
and then that all completes and you can see some of these deployment some of these activation
...done in parallel other ones were cereal you did not have to worry about that simply by
specifying a relationships and resource manager
takes care that for you so let's take a quick look at the built-in support
fragile resource managers that is...visual studio so enabling to get started with
resource manages really easily.
And, to do that I'm going to go to a new project here...the cloud section.
You can see that there's this as your resource group here unlit
...the default name.
And, visual studio has some canned resource templates
based built into it...web app...because this shows us a multi
...type application described as a resource group.
Alfie go over here to the casual resource group
solution I can click on the jason describing.
That application and this is the template underneath a database plus
a sequel server over here we see adjacent outline which is
convenient chameleon allows me to look at the resource types that are inside of this
template and there's a number of them in addition to the ones that seem obvious like the website
in the database we've got a sequel server and we've got a database and you can see as a click
...navigating through the...you can see here's a resource.
And, there's some interesting things to note here, for example, the type this is a database type it's actually
a subset of the microsoft
sequel name space it's.
Going to...specific locations so I...resource groups that spanned multiple locations meaning multiple as a
regions I can say this thing goes to east us
and this other database part of the same template that goes to west us and that will allow me to create and a single
Dr or highly available application that spans regions and asher and then you can see
properties down here with references to what are called parameters...take a look at what
parameters are like I mentioned you parameterized your resource group and this
allows you to customize it customize this template for whatever environment...to
...references here like, for example, I the size of the worker.
In the website...how big in the worker role be
...the worker be rather you see the allowed values are zero one and two it's a type
...the default value...so...no parameters to specified here's the default but it
also any tooling can look at this and know that it's going to enforce the I don't put a three and there.
Now what I'm going to do.
Here is to show you just what how
...visual studio healthy deployed this thing so I've created
an provision my asher subscription here and when I go to ploy it one of the things that can ask
...for the new resource group name but I can also at the parameters right here inside...visual studio so this is
looking the template and saying hey you need to provide somebody's values you can see the worker size here was
default to zero and specified in that parameter section of the template?
So, let's switch back to the powerpoint and get a little more detailed about.
In those templates so quickly just
to review there's some things that you saw in their parameters those.
Are the temple ties to parameters that allow us to specify values from the outside
...configuration file
...variables which are basically macros of values that I can then
use multiple places inside the template instead of having to put the same expressions all over the
place the resources that we mention and then there's output values so templates can produce output
values that then can be looked at through tooling or through...will tell us what are the interesting things that came out,
for example, when I go to ploy website what's the url
...the website the popped out of that resource group template as
...that can be and output parameter emitted by the website itself internet
research group and I can go take a look inside of a portal,
for example, to see what url to hit to see that website?
And, then there's some dsl that you'll see here and templates that allow us to do some
create expressions, for example, one of them is this parameters expression which
references a parameter you can see this reference from the second one up there that
lets us reference and output value from one resource into another one so that...
string that sql connections...mentioned I want to reference from the website configuration for
sql connection string the output of the sequel database which is going to be
...connection strength and that I do with the reference value.
So, that's a quick overview of as a resource manager let's talk about some of the announcements
we're making here build today which are really exciting surround the new support for virtual machines
storage networking api as part of this resource manager family.
Up to today we've had a number of resources already
plug-in as resource manager use saw websites you saw
...database an example I just showed you read...caches another one there's forty more.
Microsoft first party and like I mentioned some third-party like...grid,
for example, is a third-party research provider so you can provision a send grid endpoint
as part of a template and that would then allow your website to be able to send
email without you having to go provision that yourself?
There's also version one of network storage and networking api is built
...resource manager today but let's talk about what's new about version...
So, version one you can go and if you create and
the portal which I'll show you...minute resource group you will see or virtual,
virtual machine of read vone tight it will go into a resource group
but it's not a first-class citizen as a resource manager so it has no
are back support has no tagging support has no templates it's really kind of
a visual visualization a kind of weak...resource into the resource group and it's got
clunky network modeling if you familiar with our networking api is maybe wanted to have
...for example, that was separate from a virtual machine or load balance or that was separate
from a scale-up set of virtual machines you didn't have that option those were baked into
the compute model so what we've got with version to is...direct integration
and measure resource manager so all of the things I'm talking about with as a resource manager just light up
you get...control plane now that we put in here under
for to implement these resource types which overcome some of the serialism asian.
Limitations
aversion one implementation so if you've ever done multiple operations maybe had a
lock where you couldn't go update your cloud service because something was in progress you want to add a
...virtual machine that the virtual machine those are all gone everything
is fully asynchronous so you can go be modifying virtual machines...modifying
...network adapters for them while you're at modifying that virtual disks for them at the same time all of that is
than just asynchronous operations you...the control
...and then really excited to say that these new api
or part of the agile consistent private cloud experience that we're
...that were committed delivering and I'll talk more about that in a second.
Like right now let's go take a look at these new api...
So, we'll switch over the demo machine.
Now what I've got is template here this is a coffee shop application
and I've got the temple here in visual studio if I click open you can see there's a bunch of resources
in here we see a sequel server we...website just like we saw before but here we see version
two of these virtual machines we see the next as well and
when I click on the virtual machine we can see that these are fully parameterized so I can see I
parameterized the size of the virtual machine right here I parameterized things like the
admin user account and password so these are going to be ask for the time a deploy the template
I even specified where this...go into what storage
account planner parameterized way and then there's a variable here macro basically...source
...image id if I go to source...image ideas variable?
You can see that this is a concatenation of some subscription information and then there's
a parameter here when source image name so it's actually going to ask me when I
deploy this thing what the...source image
name is but there's a default and you can see that's a linux virtual...
sorry click on the wrong one here you can see this is a windows virtual machine this is server twenty-four
...so there's defaults here specified I can overrule them specify other images.
Now I'm...this empower...here's the our...command...to deploy an as a
...group you can see...this one mark copies...copy twenty-four
and specifying east us here's the jason file and then.
I'm specifying as part of this deployment a
parameters file so let's go take a look at that parameters file.
Which is right here and I've simply filled in those values that are required like I
mentioned the admin the username...password you can see there's no password there because I didn't want to show you what
password really is but if I press a five now this is...
I've got a switch to.
As a resource manager...here.
And, I press a five and now this is going to be launching.
...us I'm not going...wait for that to finish I've already deployed one of these resource groups of that
template here...copy...copy...being deployed
...click on...coffee and let's take a look at the resources that are part of it that match the template
so a click on resources here's the list a resources exactly like with on
a template like exactly like we saw in visual studio down here you can see there's a
storage account so this is the version to the storage control
...here's the blob and there's one blob in that account
and that is storing of the hd here which you saw the full parameters
...of that bhd as
...provided in that template when I go back and take a look at the web app.
Write-in here I've got a browse experience just to show you that this thing really is
live there's the copy shop app that was deployed as part of that template.
So, that's fantastic unemployment's and as your public
cloud but this copy shop business that I'm going to get into coming from...
I've...coffee and I think there's a space for
a little neighborhood type copy shop.
Maybe not near san francisco but maybe some place else and what I want to do is deployed
the same coffee shop apt to a location where I've got my little copy shops sprouting up that maybe
as your isn't reaching yet what employ to a private cloud and take that same template and
...private cloud so let's go see how I can do that?
I've got that same template here copy shop jason.
I'm deploying it here...got as...set environment this-is against as a
resource manager I've added my own copy shop.
Private...endpoint I've got a subscription at that
endpoint build demo and when I launch this thing
...asked me the resource name coffee?
Sharpe.
Let's make it to some random number.
And, now this is going to start deploying to
...cloud as part of this endpoint for
...private cloud again we're not going to wait for that to finish let me go and take a look at.
That's spartan.
Still getting used to that ux now this browser is pointing at
...private cloud where I just deployed started
that deployment when I go to browse all here's the resource groups.
There's more toffee...thirty in the process...deploying less click on the one that's already employed...coffee.
And, this is going to look very much like what we saw.
In the public interface.
Of the same template the same resources the same api as I can go click on the storage
account.
And, take a look at the blob.
The blob now...public measure sitting in the
blob storage account of my private cloud if I go back to the website.
I get the same exact portal experience click an open.
And, open...copy shop running
...private cloud same template parameterized differently private
club deployment so let's switch back to.
Now what I've shown you is the introduction of virtual machines
into this new...research manager api and what I'm going to do for the rest the session is taking up the layers
...the stack to show you some of the capabilities that were
enabling as we build this into the system I...as your consistent private
...I've shown you add your public caught...the fact that I can take a virtual machine...deployed to either one of them?
You'll see in here and this label...virtual machines...virtual machine scale sets so let's talk about
...virtual machine scale sets this is a for denounce...that's going to be coming
in a few months of vm scale sets so those of you that of
use worker roles are web roles how many of you...worker roles are web roles
and asher so a lot of you have and you probably have run into some of the limitations of
web...as powerful as they are for stateless scale out applications for
easy elasticity and reproducibility because they're all just
golden images limitations.
Include the fact that you can't pick a custom image there's no support for linux,
for example, in web and worker role so what...virtual machine scale
sets introduces is this is basically next generation worker role you don't need to put your on
...in there it's basically exactly as avert virtual machine excepted stateless and
...can scale it out very easily you can start with the...image
it supports golden image-based updates of the os so you
get reproducibility inconsistency of the experience and it's great for clusters
speaking of clusters...here's just a little graphic to show you these things
scaling up but speaking of clusters.
Let's talk about virtual machine extensions and how this enables third-party
cluster orchestrate...to layer on top of asher with virtual machine extensions
you've got the ability to dynamically inject coding configuration
...virtual machines either at the time that the virtual machines provision or even afterwards and you can even update the
coder configuration we previewed this ll basically about a year-ago and this is part of
the new virtual machine api as well you can stick things in like chef and
puppet and ds see you can stick and things like monitoring agents back-up agents we just announced
...back-up service for...virtual machines which make use of the back-up
...extensions to inject back-up agent you can
stick security agents in there that do bit locker encryption the do math basically the
...left imagination for what kind of code you want to layer and the benefit of extensions is that you don't
have to...this stuff into...image you can take any stock image...compatible
...extensions and layer them on after the fact so no more having to go and
have image sprawl just because you want to monitor agent inside of your images?
Now what this enables is for third-party cluster
...paths application frameworks to put their own
to bootstrap themselves into these virtual machines using virtual machine extensions and again they don't have to bake all this stuff
...the virtual machine they can take a
advantage of the extension model to get themselves bootstrap and they also
...get the benefit of having anything else that works is an extension work side-by-side with them like anti-virus.
You can see here...growing upthere's support for...right scale
...swarm clusters and then those can bring in their own paths layers on top
because those are cluster orchestration systems that paths.
Application frameworks layer on top of like a print the
...elastic marathon or some examples now what I'm
going to show announce here is through a great partnership with
...a sphere is if you familiar with...a sphere and its support for
...those clustering.
They have a new
cluster orchestration platform called dc os and dc os
...been private preview today we're announcing public preview and the first places public
previewing is with on as...built into templates and what I've
got right here is showing you get hub with amazes sphere template here?
...core here there's...sanders you just modified this an hour ago
he's a program manager on the virtual machine team.
And, what we
see here is that plus that template for amazes your cluster so this is a highly available
measures for cluster that you can play with this thing if I scroll down the interesting thing
...the interesting part here is how do we make this thing up high scale cluster
...here's a type microsoft virtual machines you can see that it takes a
...a parameter takes allocation of parameter but then it's got this interesting thing which is a new addition to
...a resource manager which is the ability to basically create loops over
resource instantiation so this is the master vm loop for the master nodes and that
...a sphere cluster and account is parameterized so I can say
that I want ten or three?
...a sphere masters I can say what one because I'm just doing
...and I don't want a big deployment and you can see some dependencies on some other resources zinger and
down...os profile you can see an example of somebody
extension support we've added which is custom data gets piped into the virtual machine through a cloud
...type interface so that this gets bootstrap them is a sphere master gets
dropped on-base...image again so that may
...a sphere doesn't have to continue to maintain a ios images with...for big
...you can dynamic you can pick amazes ...image...deploy the cluster into that image.
So, let's go take a look at that means a sphere cluster I'm going
to go back to that and we've built in
...deployment experience right from get hub for all of the templates and you'll see that we've
public...create created probably a hundred templates now that are up and get hub
they're all have this...as your button on it so once uses the
setup your as your subscription information you get this kind of experience which will open
a template up now if I'm happy with this template I say save.
And, then I go back to add a parameters and you see here the parameters that I need to enter so
some of them like the number of this slaves.
The number...and we're going to deploy a cluster with a hundred slaves.
And, down here we need...pipe in some sh data.
Actually I'm going to just go and skip that because I've already got this cluster
...cluster like this already deployed but I'd specify these other two parameters press ok and this would start
a deployment of a hundred vm amazes your
cluster to asher but let's go...take a look.
By going to measure portal at the predeployed one that I've got.
And, we're going to play...a little playing around amazes your cluster to show you how cool
is to have a container cluster orchestrate or on top of measure virtual
machines so I've got here this one here dc os.
And, you can see...got two hundred twelve resources these are all the resources including
next virtual machines this the masters in the slaves.
That are part of this deployment now I want to interact with this cluster so I've deployed it but now I need
to interactive the management...to
at and I can go and find out where the management interface is by looking at the.
Deployment history for this thing which has the template output parameters and you can see there's three
masters that each spit out their own urls.
Now I don't know which one is
...true master of this cluster because one of those three is the master
...three for fail over purposes now there's a fifty chance I think the right one
actually that doesn't make any sense does it there's a one-in-three chance I think the right one but it's port fifty
the things listening on and you can see a picked the wrong one and now it's redirected me to the amazes
...master and now I'm looking at the amazes cluster management interface
...dc os brings to the table is a higher-level
management interface on top amazes clusters and I can get to that.
And, now I'm looking at the dc os dashboard which shows me the overall cluster
utilization I can see the all the nodes that are part that cluster and their specific civilizations
What I want to do is?
Take a look at.
The custom a custom viewer as a deploy a bunch of container to this and we've created a dc
os visualize are working with the
...sphere team which will show us container starting up and when I?
Come back here...I'm going to do is add the marathon application framework.
To that cluster and this is
already pointing at that cluster that I just got deployed I'm going to add the spark which is another application model.
...the ads.
And, now I'm going to launch thousand marathon instances.
And, I'm an adult launch a thousand spark instances so these are all going
into darker containers on top of those virtual machines.
On top of asher...this little visualize are shows you just how quickly.
These tasks.
These application containers get deployed in launched onto that means...cluster.
I think that was amazes your guys clapping all right so let's switch back to the presentation.
So, that's a look at cluster orchestrated is on top of that foundation
of virtual machines virtual machine extensions on top of measure resource manager with templates
...you into and I already by the way talked a little
...containers this morning and the keno demo any people saw that
so consuming everybody did some...windows containers and,
linux...with integrated doctor support there's a full container session that we're going to
windows server containers tomorrow late afternoon so I'm not going to
spend time here but one of the great things about containers is that
they're great for micros service-based applications and let me just stop here for a second and talk about what
is a micros service-based application...space application is one
...application decomposed into tiny parts and you decompose...parts for a
few reasons one is that you can test them in isolation they can run
...isolation when they put them in a container you can make sure that when it works on your deb box it works
and production box at as well now
by a decomposing into this fine-grain units you want to create
kind of rigorous interfaces between one of the microsoft...and the other microsoft
...the application and that also helps you evolve those different
party application independently...strong contracts as long as you don't break the contract you can
change the implementation underneath the hood and even
add new functionality without breaking the other microsoft...that are depending on it and then have this
kind of organic growth of the application in a very lightweight and decentralized
...you can also update them independently so if you make a change the one microsoft with your not
impacting...application you can scale amount independently so
instead of having to take giant blocks that are all a whole bunch of stuff inside of it
you just want to scale-up because you hit a limit on one of the application...in that big monolithic
block you want to scale out just the microsoft...that needs to be scaled...that needs more cpu
or more network with and leave everything else alone so it has a
lot of efficiencies for agile development for rapid iteration for
...of management now going and managing all of these micros services
is something that you probably don't want to yourself you want micros service manager to do it for you and
it would even be nice if you had an application platform that understood microsoft
...made it easier for you to write applet microsoft...applications and that is
were service fabric comes into play is built on top of that same foundation that we saw them is a
sphere and dc os clusters and these other cluster orchestrated and
paths libraries on top of this is something that we've been working on inside
microsoft for a long-time and it has rich set
of functionality designer on microsoft
riff-based applications everything from making sure that is highly available
its template...just like we...resource manager you describe a template of your micros
service-based application and that allows service fabric to look at what you
want and make sure that you're getting what you want if you want three
replicas of your front-end microsoft's and a virtual machine goes down
it's service fabric is going to make sure that it's going to migrate and create that
microsoft third one they got impacted
for-you without you having to go worry about that it supports partitioning
for scale-up and I'll talk more about...supports rolling upgrades of microsoft
...so if you got those three front-ends you don't want to just blasting update all three of them you want to do
it in a careful way that provides availability and safety by doing
...one of my top one-at-a-time and if there's a problem with health watchdogs built into service fabric
...ones that you add yourself you can get rollback on top of it?
It supports private clouds as well as private-public clouds as well so you can
put on your own systems you can deploy to asher.
Here's...it's just a subset of the some of the high-level functionality and capabilities of service fabric
I've touched on some of them I talked about rolling update with rollback support strong versioning so it
knows what rollback means because it knows that you're you've got version to of microsoft's
...version one is the last known good one
...support side-by-side support so I can even actually deployed version
tool microsoft's on the same cluster with version one and service fabric will
route requests appropriately depending on what the client lots to talk to version to
...version one in supports leadership election and this is inherent in something
called stateful service staple microsoft support which I'll talk about in a second of course name
discovery that's any cluster orchestrated with containers needs name discovery service...can different parts
the application...each other I mention...supports partitioning support it supports load
balancing placement constraints now this is important if you've got a clustering your
deploying multiple applications to it or a
...complex application with many microsoft mrs you might say
the front-ends can't be on the same servers with the middle tier.
Or some other component because they conflict on resource requirements
or they conflict in some other way so what we'll do is set price constraints to say these microsoft
mrs can't be co-located with these other ones you can even do things like these
two need to be together because they actually have a tight interface
...what round-trip communication between them to be as fast as possible so on the
local machine where can be and like I mention this is the only
kind of micros service application platform out there that supports stateful micros
services I'll talk more about what stateful micros services means in a second but this
what we're making available is already like I said been used for five years now inside
...our all of these services for everything from as
your database which is mouths running one-point-four
million customer databases let me just highlight what that means from service
fabric perspective that means tens of thousands a...hundreds of thousands...containers microsoft
resp essentially micros services each one of those databases is represented as an instance
of stateful micros services...with either three or four replicas where service fabric is
taking care of all the state management and all of the healing and all of the updating of
those database instances so one-point-four times roughly three that gives you an idea of the number
statefull replica instances that service fabric right now as we speak is keeping healthy
...a cloud down to things like into and core...so core
...is supporting...billions requests per second people making
...all of that is going through service fabric and this isn't what we're giving
out as the sdk here today to you which they url should be live about now which I'll show you at the end of
the slide we're not giving you something that is looks like what we run internally for
this stuff we're not getting something that's a rewrite of it we're giving the exact same
bits this sdk that you're getting is the same sdk that all of these services u?
So, that's why examines exciting let me just give you an idea of some of the things that can do
visually so I've got to applications consisting...multiple microsoft
...deployed it with placement constraints and load balancing it's gone out to
a cluster of machines now for machine fails service
amicable automatically heal those instances to other.
What is a microsoft...the role of service
...really whatever you want to be a can be...dot net five application it can be
no js application in fact they can just be an arbitrary exhibit you say this
is my microsoft's and take it from here anything you want to be?
And, as I mentioned several times now there's two types of microsoft...that service
fabric supports their stateless microsoft mrs in their stateful microsoft...ones are the ones that
were probably most familiar with...the whole application model that address been pushing towards
...a stateless one stateless worker...and web roles and sp dot
net web apps those all external...state to some place else and there's
a need for stateless microsoft mrs in any complex application as your database consistent probably
doesn't micros services and several of them are stateless micros services like front-ends.
Then there's stateful microsoft mrs now here let's talk about what stateful
...means it means that the code...the compute
...co-located together it's not externalizing their
ballad tightly together and the only through this kind of micros service
statefull system can-you insurer high availability and durability
...state and service fabric takes care of that state management for the developer
data...database.
Badger database developers they worry about running sequel
...and underneath...diag the they talk to service fabric api is
...sequel that actually wants to make a transaction they call service fabric api and
service fabric api is then take care of
making sure that the primary in that leadership election one of those three database replicas
is the primary that state that state change that transaction is replicate
...the secondary is developer doesn't worry about it doesn't even worry about the fact that it's
on a primary secondary the secondary is are tracked by service fabric and if there's a
failure anywhere along the way if there's an update...progress on one of the databases so
it's down service fabric takes care of creating new instance in the database
...server and catching that instance up with the primary
and the other surviving secondary or if it's the primary the
...service fabric picks a new primary and
the name service automatically routes requests to the new primary providing a
statefull consistent view of data very easy for this...developers to work on.
Now there's two different...types of api there's multiple program
allows you can put on top of service fabric I'm going to talk about too that were releasing as part of this sdk
one is called the reliable services api and the other one's called the reliable...api
let's talk about the reliable services api those of you are familiar with dot...many of
our dot...to hair-raising...so how many of you have ever used
to dictionary or collection so almost everybody has.
What we're releasing
here are support for reliable collections and reliable
dictionaries basically reliable services using the same?
...that you're familiar with except underneath the hood service fabric is taking care of making
them highly available durable using microsoft these microsoft mrs underneath so reliable
...reliable dictionaries and let's go take a look.
At a demo which you can get right from visual studio.
One of these sample applications so if I go on that visual studio now when you get the
...cancel you'll see service fabric here and I can say application stateless service stateful service
stateless actor servers and stateful actor service of click on statefull service impress ok.
And, then we'll go take a look this has one basically micros services part of it here's the
application manifest so remember I said everything's declarative you can see that this has
one stateful service it's called statefull one is of type
statefull here.
And, it's partition I'll talk more about partition
in a second but we can go take a look at the code for this
...service and this code is right here so this is getting a
reference to a reliable dictionary which is just a key value store here it's
sticking in my dictionary and then what is doing is getting the current
value for the key counter one?
And, then it spitting out that value right here so this will
...service fabrics diagnostic logs that we can see in a second and then
it's adding one here and then...committing this transaction so transactions
are transparent essentially transparent to you can perform multiple operations on multiple
objects.
All underneath this kind of transaction this create transaction.
And, then it's all either committed or documented so I can go up
this object this object do that one minus this.
Say commit and even the whole thing happens or not...happened and
they this failure cases are all handle automatically for-you underneath...
The states are replicated those replicas in
a transaction consistent manner and that's how easy it is to write a statefull
...consistent application with this api
now let's go ahead and deployed this thing so I'm going to deploy it by.
Saying publish.
...need to say deploy.
Actually we just.
...actually I don't...to...so I've got a test cluster set up for this one and
the development cluster and what...do is an
...five sorry and visual studio and what this is going to do start to
...spit up those logs?
Those...fabric diagnostic logs right here individual studio diagnostic events so
we're going to first see those microsoft
...that micros in those instances because they're going to...instances deployed.
And, then we're going to start to see counters here.
...counter one counter to counter three.
That's the incrementing of
that reliable dictionary key value and I can go back here individual,
individual studio in the service and I can get.
Debugging of that stateful micros service rights...visual studio so I'm
just hit this you can see I've got all my locals I can step through it so this is distributed
...debugging right from inside a visual studio.
So, let's go back to the powerpoint let me talk a little bit more about some of...capabilities
and show you some demos that a little bit more impressive than some running something in visual studio at least I hope
Microsoft partitioning we know that
we're in a scale out world we're dealing with datasets that are so large that we need to
...we can't scale-up so partitioning is one way that helps us do this having client
...routed to a partition of microsoft...so I can
...microsoft name space and as request come into new partition the
microsoft as instances are automatically...up with by service fabric so you can see here that I've
got one partition with its primary and secondary is another partition serving the same.
With its as well and these get distributed just like any other microsoft
Let's go take a look at some of
...action on a larger-scale application how many people noticed just
...curiosity that...always...new always wears a red shirt.
Anybody notice that I so it turns out a lot of people notice
that and there's a lot of people have a lot of debate and discussion about which of
...scott's red shirts of the best.
Over the various events facebook so we created a application
...that's going to let people vote on which
...goo red shirt may like the best and this is the composition is broken down into microsoft
...a web your micros service...national service counting micros service which counts up all the
...from all the counties in the country those county services are just keeping track of...in their own
county and then we've got voting services which are generating votes this kind of a...generator for the application so let's
switch to the taking a look at this application.
And, what I'm going to do is open the website here?
And, you can see that I don't have anything running but what I'm going
to do is launch this and this is the deploy election from package so I've deployed this
...application by the way here's this guy
go application and I'm going to deploy this and come back and show you.
Now this is a refreshing here and this will come up in a second as
that application of this is being deployed by the way to microsoft
...to a hundred eighty...up and adder ten...for the initial county's.
...gforce for the...scale out...going...do in a minute five
...that are doing the national service level and five
...are the web interface so this is a massively scaled application running
...it's going to be deploying micros services to this cluster to represent this application here
and a second auc this fire up.
And,...start to come in and do little refresher and there we see build thirteen
...twenty fourteen and the votes are coming in
and the counties are starting to let up with their preferences so they're colliding up...color
for the majority vote in those counties if I go take a look at the code for this?
This is that I'm in
the vote controller actually let me go to the national election service.
Of yet here I am and this is actually going to.
Down here getting the reliable dictionary this is the county vote count.
If I click on this reliable dictionary county data you can see
the here's the structure it's got its own dictionary of the shirts and it's keeping track of
...per second per county.
this is doing a link query across all of their reliable dictionaries for all of the
counties and doing a summation on them to show us the result
by shirt which is what we're...that you...and that's how easy it is all of this is
du-rable consistent highly available and that's a link query across the whole thing.
Go back here now I go to
the cluster view and this is where things get interesting here's the cluster with all the microsoft
...with a custom ux that we built to show you.
And, actually this looks like it's.
Might be still deploying so here's the throughput of the votes that were saying.
And, this is going to continue to rise as we get more and more these now what I've done.
Is could set of placement constraint such that these microsoft
...can only sit on this these nodes and I'm only looking at the county
...the ones where the county?
Aggregators are...
What I'm going to do is lift that placement constraint?
And,...that placement constraint by first connecting to the service fabric endpoint.
then here this you can see placement constraints on a...placement restraint...eight.
And, now we're going to see this thing like spread out all over the place.
You should see the start to go...here and a second.
And, you can see start to see that...to migrate and in the
...time...another...so we're going to see the whole all of these micros
services get spread out across the rest of the cluster.
Just automatically happening with the lifting that placement constraint and that remember this is
stateful data that's being migrated all of those counts for this counties are being migrated as part of
that these operations so that's a quick look at that let's switch back to the powerpoint.
And, we have one last.
Demo to show you and this one is a reliable
...api how many people have heard of project orleans.
How many people have heard of the actor model...actor...so quite a few of, you
know, the reliable...api lets you build basically object-oriented microsoft
mrs ones where the...the state the lifecycle management is all done by the actor
programming management interface you just worry about the object and the
objects talk to each other through messages and activation happens automatically by reference
an actor that doesn't exist in an actor object doesn't exist and instance the actor
framework automatically instantiates it and I'll have to worry about it if it becomes
...against...torn down from ram and basically status persisted on-disk it gets
activity and that happens automatically we've written a little game
...help highlight this called actor voids?
Where each object in the game and this is kind of because project orleans-and being used by
...online where everything's an actor inhale online kind of like this...actor the
ship as an actor the ships the asteroids or each individual actors and
the laser beams or bolts are all individual actors and the system all talk to each other
through actor message-passing let's switch back to the demo machine and take a look at
Source code.
I've got actor words up here and running here's the actor I'd what I'm going to do is publish this?
Deploy this.
And, right click.
Deploy.
And, this is going to deploy this too windows
service fabric cluster that's already operating and while.
That's launching I'll show you the asteroid actor which here
it's activation method simply registers a timer that is going to
call move asteroid move asteroid simply updates the position of the actor
and that's it now let me pull this game up an effort to show you this demo...bring
...sanders up and we're going to play a little afterwards.
Okay, so, amazing I think this is me
...the snir the best worry...the best...presentations right now because I'm onstage.
Thanks work they agreed...we like you thank you that gory.
They have no idea who I am.
Wake-up your xbox controller.
...got disconnectednotes allows...you are those an accident.
Another anything happening,... what's going on with yours.
Actually this...working...you can imagine would be like if...
...be really honest...really fun actually the keyboard word
...the keyboard work okay if does make you...
...on your slides...over the place.
...we get you back on...because I want to show you...was going to...you.
And, that's by updating this game it live getting, getting I'm here, yeah.
Thanks core his...worth my dogs...my done as
...can go...you everybody...course...
All right so...was going to do is this is I've got a code
snippy here the answer to that is going to make this the asteroids evil for...
He didn't know that and then when I was going to do is I need to update the version of this?
I need to set the assembly information to new version so service fabric
knows it's new then I'll come up to the application and I'll say build.
And, what I'm going to do is this is going to start a rolling update?
So, I'm...say package.
And, I'm going to go to perishable now.
Nsa upload this is just
...that...updated version will go back to the game.
So, we're going to rolling update now that packages uploaded.
And, then that started a rolling update...
...to rowing update there's...rolling update and.
Now what's going to happen here is these asteroids are going to sleight start to turn red and of
...was up here playing set of...out like he did we would see.
The asteroids are going to turn red and start to follow his ship.
So, as the rolling update proceeds.
...just take a few seconds.
There we go and what they're going to do is they're going to follow...
Thinkers backstage buying...
And, you can see that there's no...of the game these
...instances these actors are getting upgraded while we're playing a game
in changing your logic...zero downtime as I continue to play the game
all happening again through the magic and these are all...actors with multiple replicas.
So, you can you get the idea that's the game.
All right now one last thing that you are use...backstage aren't.
So, one last thing I want to show you is
...from unless I soft which has been using service fabric for a while and
let's hear what they have to say about it and then I'll give you some...some other sessions and we'll wrap it up.
By the way as I soft is operational intelligence company was known...resources are not
...and...look at the california what we're
going through right now we're going to a record drought we need to manage to resource that we have.
...now is just a giant explosion in the number of
sensors what we really need is a system
...confide...for all this data our capturing the only way to do that...to have
...in a public cloud.
...set of...system services
...output consumer and the utilities to gain insights
...actually be able to manage these resources real-time technologies
...business we data-driven to critical piece for us
...we get the right data the right time to be able use effectively microsoft
...platform concerts property reading enables us to capture the data from that
proliferation sensors and do something meaningful efficient...service fabric brings
...level of reliability and performance that we couldn't get by just using the
standard virtual machine technologies to provide a pop for us to build new technologies within
...and actually be able to bring them back on...which is important
...customers for the kinds of classic problem we're trying to solve service product
...is the only platform that makes sense for us to build ourselves it would've been
...actual undertaking for us we want to concentration where we
...leverage the platform?
Right so let's...back and I'll give you some a little bit of a
roadmap into what you're getting today with service fabric and then point
...some other video so today languages are
cplus-plus and csharp we've got other languages coming operating systems today is windows linux is
...be coming containers right now is job objects on windows you'll see containers on windows
linux and finally integration with...today
...an sdk there's the url the sdk which is live now and future will have research
providers...service fabric that will may cluster management simpler.
And, then that basically takes me
...through the whole stack of course you want to get higher-level we saw web apps this morning
and app service as the higher-level programming
model on top of measure compute platform that flushes it out from
high control to high productivity and then finally
...other sessions that we've got...go deeper into service fabric in the containers and
to resource manager into the new vtwo versions of these api is without I want to thank you very much I
hope you have a great conference and how plan on answer and with service?